Inventory of the Charlotte Ellen Martin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charlotte Ellen Martin papers
1941-1988
1944-1945
2014C6
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder (1.4 linear feet)
Memoirs, diary, correspondence, financial records, printed matter and photographs relating to the Japanese occupation of the Philippines during World War II. Includes papers of Cecil John Martin, husband of Charlotte Martin, a port captain of Cebu City and the owner and founder of the Cebu Stevedoring Company.
Martin, Charlotte Ellen, 1904-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2013.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Charlotte Ellen Martin was born in Fennville River, Illinois, May 1904. At age six, she moved to the Cebu Island in the Philippines where her father Bob worked as a businessman. Martin came back to the Philippines after high school and met Cecil John Martin whom she later married. C. J. Martin was a businessman and master seaman who founded and owned The Cebu Stevedoring Company where he navigated through the straits of Cebu and surrounding islands.
At the outbreak of World War II, Charlotte Martin signed up for duty first working for United States Army Forces in the Far East (USAFFE) in the Office of the Surgeon Force. Then, she was heavily involved in the Red Cross and later, worked for the Army's Office of Strategic Service, (O.S.S.) in Washington, D.C. providing U.S. Army forces with intelligence in the field in order for OSS to help train anti-Japanese guerrilla movement in the Philippines--because she knew the culture and spoke the language fluently. Evidence of her second language is demonstrated in letters to the presidents of The Philippine Commonwealth, Sergio Osmeña, Jr. and Manual Acuña Roxas.
By 1942, The Japanese Imperial Army had occupied many strategic areas of the archipelago. Charlotte Martin went into hiding on the advice of a military friend. Many Filipino, Spanish and Americans hid from Japanese Imperial Forces in fear of experiencing the atrocities that were widely reported. Martin hid in the hills and mountains of Cebu, Leyte and Mindanao avoiding the Japanese until November 1943 when she was rescued by submarine and taken to Australia ending her ordeal.
This experience became the basis of her book that she wanted published entitled “Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs” which was subsequently censored and reviewed by the War Department and then rejected by major publishers because of the sensitive nature of the information in the book. Nevertheless, Martin's story is a first person account of how she survived in hiding from enemy forces.
After World War II, Martin became friends with President Sergio Osmeña (born in Cebu City) and was invited to attend his daughter's wedding in New York. When she came back to the Philippines from Washington, DC, she embedded herself into the threadwork of Filipino life once again. Martin was a board member of the Women's Club, the Girl Scouts and the Cebu City Rotary Club. Much later, C. John Martin sold The Cebu Stevedoring Company in October 1968.
In 1969, Cebu City adopted C. John Martin and Charlotte Ellen Martin as official "son" and "daughter" of their city as a gesture of gratitude for helping the community during and after the Philippine invasion. When her husband passed away in 1971, Charlotte sold their estate in Cebu. She remained a citizen of the United States enabling her to travel and to receive benefits she rightfully deserved but at painstaking cost. As the sale of her husband's company closed, Ms. Martin moved to San Francisco, California.
Scope and Conten of Collection
Personal files, including notes, photographs, manuscripts, writings, newspaper clippings, ephemera and copies of Charlotte E. Martin’s "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs," pertain to Charlotte Ellen Martin’s life on Cebu Island and surrounding regions in the Philippines during World War II to late 1960s and her life back home in the United States.
Americans--Philippines.; Osmena, Sergio,--1916-1984.; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.
- Personal Files, 1942-1988
  Scope and Contents note
  The personal business files of Cecil John Martin (C.J. Martin) and Charlotte Martin regarding records and business transactions of C.J. Martin's Cebu Stevedoring Company, disability claims, medical paperwork, exam reports under the War Claims Act of 1948. Records of war claim applications for under different acts of congress for Charlotte Martin include correspondence, inventory, blue prints of their home and other legal documents. Includes printed materials, certificates, awards, clippings, programs and ephemera.
  - C.J. Martin files, 1942-1968 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - C.J. Martin files, 1944-1961 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - C.J. Martin files, 1944-1962 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - War claims, 1944-1962 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - War claims, 1944-1965 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Printed materials, 1940-1969 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Rotary Club and other materials, 1947-1982 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - City of Cebu, Adoption Ceremony materials, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - "Glenda Crytser's 1941 Philippine Adventure,", undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Correspondence, 1942-1988
  Letters and telegrams from her friends, family and agencies like the Red Cross, the United States, Office of Strategic Services (OSS). Includes ephemera and correspondence with President (of the Commonwealth of the Philippines) Sergio Osmeña.
  - Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1988 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - C.J. Martin to Charlotte Martin, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Grimm family correspondence regarding the Cebu Stevedoring Company, 1966-1977 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Grace Chenowyth and Kathryn Sharp, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Tom Jurika, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - E.W. Mill, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Philippine Commonwealth President Sergio Osmeña Jr., 1944-1961 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Writings and Related Materials, 1941-1981
  Martin wrote a draft and manuscript entitled, “Two jumps ahead of the Japs: A story of an American woman’s experiences in occupied territory,” from about 1944 to 1945. Manuscripts of this text range up to 232 pages including word counts. “Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs” is her first person account of her survival in enemy occupied territory in the Philippines during World War II. Martin also tells of things she heard through military friends who help her hide. Includes correspondence about the manuscript and the radio broadcast that took place on March 23, 1945 in San Francisco, California.
  - Brief Chronology of the Philippine Campaign, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "American Fugitives in the Philippines,", 1944 October (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Notebook, 1942 June - 1943 December (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs: A Story of an American Woman's Experiences in Occupied Territory," original manuscript, circa 1944 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs," edited, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs," War Department review copy, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs," typed manuscript, circa 1981 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs," correspondence, 1944-1982 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs," KYA Radio broadcast, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Photographs, 1942-1970 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  Pictorial works of Charlotte Martin’s travels within Cebu City, Cebu, Philippine Islands and the United States along with a color slide and photo of herself for the book, "Two Jumps Ahead of the Japs." Subjects include her husband, family, Philippine presidential family members and United States military personnel. Pictorial works of General MacArthur, military photographer Gae Faillace and Imelda Marcos.